Hey guys, Shadite welcome to concept
encoding and today in spring boot
microser video we are going to set up
two microservices and the first thing we
will do is communicate with each other
right. So let's start without wasting
any time. So this would be our goal
setting up of two microser service and
product service which would be running
on different port number right. So order
service we will make it run on 8081 and
product service
8082. And how two microservices can
communicate with each other? This is our
goal. Right? It's not very simple. There
are different ways. And
in spring microservices or spring cloud
what is the recommended way of approach?
So we have to see that. So let's
start setup of two microservices. The
first one is order service. As we have
already know how to set up any spring
boot project, we have already covered so
many topics. So we know
that how to make use of spring
initializer. So here I am creating one
order
service right just creating with spring
web for now not uh adding a spring cloud
just a spring web for now.
Similarly, I'm setting up one product
service again very very basic project
for now. We are starting with the
scratch like setting up very basic
project itself spring web. So now I have
this
two projects. Now in the order service
in its
application.properties I have put the
port number
8081. Right? And when I started it, this
order service is started on port number
8081. Similarly, whatever the project
which got which we have downloaded from
here, if you open it up and change in
the application.properties server. 8082
and started. So our product service
application going to start on 8082.
Now in our system two applications are
running product service and order
service on different port number. Now
when two service are running the first
thing we have to do is how they can
communicate between each other right
this is very very important like you can
say that this is the fundamental of
microser okay and we have to understand
it very clearly. So there are two
different ways synchronous and
asynchronous. So we are going to start
with first synchronous
communication. So synchronous
communication means client wait for the
response from server before continuing.
So now let's say in this case our order
service is going to
call product service. Okay. So at any
point of time it start the synchronous
communication. So order service will
wait for the response of the product
service. Okay. So you can say that it's
a blocking
nature. Blocking in
nature. Okay. Means thread wait till
response is not received.
So synchronous communication types are
rest template, rest client and f client.
So this is very important. This is
actually which is used
in spring
cloud. Okay. And you know that whenever
we are working with microservices we are
ultimately have to use spring cloud
because it has very well integration
with all the other tools like load
balancer service discovery observability
etc. Okay. So we have to use an spring
cloud and in spring
cloud this communication type is used.
But if we directly jump into the fing
client and understand about it, our base
would not be clear. So to first set up
our base, we have to understand rest
template and rest client. Okay, which
are the you can say that mode of
communication between
microservices but without a spring cloud
without a spring cloud. Okay, if you are
not using spring cloud means if you are
not using uh ureka server service
discovery and all like all the
microservices which we are going to
cover in future if we are not using
spring cloud
functionality then these two are
sufficient to communicate between the
microservices but as I mentioned
whenever we are because in future we are
going to use spring cloud for our
microservices and this is the
communication we have to use but to
understand it better. We have to
understand these two then only our base
would be clear how faint client is also
working because internally it might be
using the same flow
only. So let's start here in this we see
a sample HTTP get
request call. So this is a very very
basic get request. So what request
contains get call. So here first we have
a get method
like HTTP method which is like get,
post, put, delete. This is my URI. This
part is my URI, right? Uh what is the
path which you are hitting? So in the
product service which I am trying to hit
here. This is the API actually. Okay.
This is the HTTP protocol. So we have
different HTTP protocol 1.0 1.1 2 3. So
these are the protocol version which we
are using for the
HTTP host like the target host where our
product services like so this is the
port number URL and port number user
agent is nothing but a client or tool
which is used to make the request so now
let's say I'm using curl URL to make or
initiate an endpoint if you are using
postman so that agent would be written
like which tool you are using to
actually invoke the request
except format in which client want
response. Okay. So if you want uh server
that hey return me the response in the
application uh JSON format then you have
to add this. So this is a very very
basic HTTP request call. Okay. And this
is how very very basic HTTP post request
call looks like. So I'm just telling you
that so that we are in a same page right
when we are calling HTTP method we know
what it is when we are saying protocol
what protocol URI what is the URI okay
when we are saying target host because
in future we are going to use lot of
word host so host means this UR URL and
port number
okay so how does HTTP post request calls
look like again same HTTP method URI
protocol your target host agent accept
this is all same but what extra so we
have content type so in the post we also
have a
body like request object right what we
have to send so this content type
tells request body which I'm going to
send you is
JSON okay and the content length tell
the number of bytes in the request
request body what is the length of it
bytes in
bytes and then this is the actual body
or you can say that actual data like
let's say in the post request we are
generally creating a new object so a new
product object which I have just for
example so
I'm sending the body here so this is how
HTTP post request call look
like
and let's see how the response call look
like a very basic
very very important because lot of
things we are going to cover
which very very tightly coupled with the
response call like keep alive I'll tell
you so again here if you see we have
content type because now we are talking
from the perspective of response like
from the server perspective so content
type is that tells client to expect JSON
response content length is number of
bytes in response
body. Okay, this is your response body
like what server is sending in the JSON
format. Now here if you see these two
things very very
important connection keep alive and keep
alive time out equals to 5 max equals to
50. Till now what we know is
that
HTTP and
websocket till now what we know is that
HTTP first create a connection right
first set up a
connection after that it send a request
then it will send a
response and after that it terminates
the
connection. But in the web soocket let's
say you have a request like again it
built a connection because it's also
based on TCP so it built the connection
request
response but web socket is persistent in
nature right persistence in nature means
that connection do not terminates and
also it is
birectional okay but what my point here
trying to say is that connection is not
terminated websocket It is persistent in
nature and what we know is that for HTTP
every time a connection is made after
request and response the connection get
terminated but this was the behavior of
1.0 HTTP protocol version 1.0 in
1.1 the
default behavior is this keep alive
connection is keep alive is set.
What does keep alive
means? So by default connection is set
to keep alive in HTTP
1.1. In HTTP 1.0 by default connection
is set to close. Whenever connection is
set to here close so what would happen
here is this behavior will follow after
connection request response and after
that connection get closed. But in 1.1
which is the default this connection is
keep alive. So what will happen
is it will not close the
connection as soon as possible. You can
say that it will not close the
connection after response. It will close
the connection based on this
configuration. So first is time out.
Time out five means close the TCP
connection if it's idle for 5 seconds
and max equals to 50 means tell the
maximum number of request can be sent
over the same TCP
connection. So you are saying that now
our HTTP protocol is also
persistent means it is not get
closed just after server send the
response in 1.1 keep alive is set and
with that these two configuration comes
into the picture where timeout tells
that close it if it is idle for this
much amount of time and this tell that
on a single TCP connection this is the
maximum number of requests
can be
processed maximum number of requests can
be sent over the same TCP connection.
Okay. So this is one flow when keep is
set. So here if you see first three-way
handshake happen between the client and
server. This is where TCP connection
buildup. Okay. After that client send a
HTTP request which I already showed you
how the HTTP request looks like. Now the
client uh server respond with the HTTP
response. But here if you see that
connection is not closed. The client may
reuse the same TCP connection again
because in the response keep alive
connection is used. Okay. So till this
configuration is
fulfilled you can reuse the connection.
So same TCP connection can be used for
multiple HTTP requests and once it is
all done either timeout happened or
maximum limit reached the four-way
termination to close the TCP connection
happen. So TCP termination happen of
this
connection. Okay. And you know that when
the connection is set to close in the
response when the connection is set to
close after
response the connection get closed. Okay
you can't use the same connection
again that's the difference.
So we will see that because our code
flows differs when this keep alive is
set. I will show you how. Okay. But by
this point of time we should be clear
how our request call looks like, how our
post request looks like, response and
what is the purpose of keep
alive.
Okay. Now let's first see I told you of
three right rest
template, rest
client and the faint
client. So these are all used in spring
boot. So spring boot you can say that
it's a layer or framework which hide
certain functionality from us which make
things little bit easy for us. But I
will say that
like what if we try to invoke the rest
endpoint without using this spring boot
itself first. Okay. What if we try to
use it with plain Java? Because even if
we use rest
template because since it's a spring
communication type, it might abstract
something from us which we don't know
internally. It might be using some
behavior which is used in plain Java. So
we first need to understand how if we
are not using the spring boot if we want
to just communicate with two microser
using plain java how we can do that
because we ultimately know that the
spring boot let's say if rest template
I'm using internally it might be using
that
only okay so
that's the first thing we will see so
here if you see the order service I am
writing one
controller I'm writing one rest
controller
This is the endpoint which I am
exposing. Similarly, for product
service, I am writing one controller /
product and this is the endpoint. Okay.
So my purpose is that order service has
to invoke this API of the product
service. this endpoint / product / id
and it will simply return this product
fetch with id whatever the id I'm just
printing for very very simple just
returning whenever this get method get
invoked simply return this now from
order service I have to invoke this okay
so I have written
this method get order okay so whenever
this endpoint get invoked from here I am
trying to invoke
this but now I am using plain Java no
spring boot template let's see what all
thing we have to
do so this is the first
thing we have to create a HTTP URL
connection object okay HTTP URL
connection object consider is as an
envelope like where we define what is
our HTTP method Get what is our content
type? JSON
application/JSON what is the type
timeout right connection timeout read
timeout so these all things we have to
specify so consider as an
envelope where we specify what is the
URL also like URL where what exactly has
to be invoked okay so provide me the
address so all these things has to be
first created so how we create we create
a first object of URL URL. Okay. You
provide the URL which we have to hit. So
I provided a URL here. Okay. Now I am
opening a
connection open connection. So at this
point of time it is not creating any. So
this is my client. This is my server. So
when I say that open connection, it is
not creating an HTTP connection now. No.
So currently it is just creating a
HTTP URL connection object at this point
of time and it
set header properly like if you want to
set body just set the body right and the
URL we have set. Okay. So everything we
have set till now the connection timeout
ret time out. Connection timeout means
now when your client is trying to
connect with server the first TCP
connection while building how much time
client should wait. How much time within
how much time this connection should get
build up. If it is taking more time then
request should get
failed. And the second one is read
timeout. Read timeout means after the
connection is built up after TCP
connection is built up the client sent a
request now client is I told you it's a
blocking nature right so client is
waiting for the response from the server
so how much time client can wait for the
response okay so that's when read time
out okay how much time client can wait
for the response from the server so this
is all we can set into this object HTTP
URL connection object
Now this is the second part.
Okay. So now we have to create a TCP
connection. So TCP connection can
generally build when out of one of these
three things are used. Either you call
connect HTTP URL connection HTTP URL
connection dot connect. Either this time
a TCP connection is built up actual TCP
connection got built up means three-way
handshake happens or if you call get
input stream or get response code which
internally calls connect only. Okay. So
it initiate the TCP connection at this
point of time. So I am directly reading
uh doing HTTP URL connection dot get
input stream. So internally it will
first do connect for me. So it will
first create TCP connect then it will
send a request for me because request is
also present in HTTP URL connection and
that get input stream. So it will give
me an input stream where response is
present. So it will also get a response
and it will give me an input stream. Now
from this input stream I have to read
the response. That's all. So now I am
reading the response from the input
stream and I'm
printing response
is whatever the string which is
returned. So it returned this product
fetch with ID
this. So that's what it printed. The
response is product fetch with ID this
one. Okay. So this is the second part.
Second part is like we actual TCP
connection is made either one of this
three and since I am using input stream
it automatically do a
connection and then internally it send
the request get the response and give me
the input stream and from that input
stream I read the response and parse it
like how I want it. If I want to parse
it as a string I just put use a string
builder. If you want to parse it as an
object, you can create an object and do
a proper mapping. Once that done, this
is the third part
is very very important. See that I am
closing the connection
disconnect. Okay. So here if you see
this is the code of the disconnect. What
it
does? It says that if input stream is
not fully read. So whatever the response
which you get if there is some issue
with that some exception you got and
this input stream is not read
properly http client close server close
the TCP
socket close the TCP connection so HTTP
client so this TCP connection
right in in Java the wrapper around this
TCP connection is known as HTTP P
client. Okay. So we are actually closing
it. If you go inside this HTTP URL
connection dot disconnect. So internally
if
it response is not properly read it
close this TCP connection. If response
is properly done it just say finished.
It do not close it. Why? Because I told
you that in
1.1 keep alive is set to
true where here keep alive is set to
true. So there what happen is there is
something a cache is maintained. Okay
the cache we have the key and value.
key is your you can say
that your host URL or port
number. Okay, this is your key URL and
port number. Okay, and value is your
HTTP client object. HTTP client is
wrapper around TCP connection. So you
can say that this is actually a TCP
connection. So for one URL and port
number you can say that for one target
host the TCP client HTTP client object
or TCP connection is stored against
it. So whenever we did
this, so whenever first we reuse it, so
whenever we do dot connect right, so it
will not directly just create a new HTTP
client object for us because this is
where actually TCP connection is made.
TCP connection you can say that HTTP
client is a wrapper around it. So HTTP
client object is actually
created. So when we do dot connect, it's
not like it blindly create a new HTTP
client object. No, it first check the
cache. It first check the cache. If
cache has this key, whatever
the this localhost
8082, right? This is the host and the
URL and the port number. Right? So if
this key is there it will reuse
the HTTP client object means it is
trying to reuse it and just change it to
let's say in use flag is set to true in
use this this connection is currently in
use as soon as we did HTTP finish we are
returning to this cache back again
making it like in use no false now it is
not in
So this HTTP connection stay valid till
this configuration as I showed you
above this time out and max.
Okay. And ultimately so here this is the
third step I'm doing. So this is our
plain
Java looks like if you want to
communicate between two
microservices. And here if you see that
now I'm hitting this API order one. So
I'm hitting this API. So what it will do
is it will try to communicate it. So
order call successfully. This is the
last order call successfully. And here I
am printing response right in the log
system. And so here so it calls the
product and print what the product
return this product fetch with id one.
But you can clearly see the disadvantage
of above approach. Too much boilerplate
code. You have to open a connection. You
have to set a header. You have to read
the response. You have to close the
streams. Right. So here if you see that
so many things you are doing. You have
to understand about HTTP URL connection.
How you setting the headers timeouts.
This stream you got right response
stream you have to read it. You have to
make sure that properly stream is closed
right. So everything you have to parse
the response by yourself. Everything you
have to handle it. So too much
boilerplate
code. Response should be handled
manually. I told you right. You are
parsing over the stream and you are
parsing how you want it. like I want
like I just simply parts the input
stream as like I'm just in the string
builder I am taking it line by line okay
I'm reading a line and just appending it
into the string builder so I want to
parse it as a string if you want to
parse or map it to an object you have to
handle it manually how if server is
sending JSON let's say product
name some price then you want to map it
to some object then you have to take
care of the mapping properly Now this is
not a string
right limited support for advanced
feature connection pooling
interceptor filters right so that's some
of the disadvantage I would say that for
the plain Java concept biggest is that
too much boiler code like too much like
here just to make one connection see the
amount of code you have written
okay that's where rest template comes
into the picture so this This is our
first spring based communication type
and we know that spring abstract lot of
things for us. It makes lot of things
easy for us. Okay. So I would say that
it's a legacy way to call rest API in a
spring application. In a spring also it
is a legacy because after rest
template rest client comes into the
picture which is the latest one. So rest
template sometime when we call rest
template we call it as a legacy way to
communic call rest AP in a spring
application in a spring application
right so now let's see the same thing
the same thing order service has to
communicate the product service if in
the rest template I have to do what I
have to do the first thing is we have to
create an object of the rest template
okay so in the app config configuration
I am creating a bean of it. We already
have seen this in depth in previous
videos. Right? So in the configuration
I'm creating one bean and I am creating
just new rest template object. That's
all simple.
Okay. This leave it for now. This is
like or I will come back again. But for
now like I have used this. So either
this or this you can say that I will
come to this. Here I am setting the
timeouts. We'll come to that. But let's
say that I have no I don't want to set
time out for now. I want default timeout
whatever connection time out read
timeout.
Right? The first thing again I just
created a simple rush template
object. Then what this is the order API
I have created the same thing from here
I would invoke
this product API. I have to invoke this.
So here if you
see whatever the object I have created I
have autodired it. So because of this
auto object is already there present
right. So this object would get autoired
here and just I'm calling rest template
dot get for
object pass the URL properly
right proper URI just pass it and what
how your response looks like. So I want
my response to be automatically parsed
in a string and ultimately my response I
get in a string
itself. So what I have done is again I
have created an object of rest template
using that object I invoke get for
object method. In the get for object
method, I pass the URI which I want to
invoke and what my response looks like
either a string or either some object I
want to mention it here. Whatever the
response I'm getting, I want to parse it
as a string. Spring boot will
automatically take care of mapping it.
whatever the streams response stream
comes in spring will automatically map
it and ultimately I get a response and
I'm just printing response from product
API called from order service is this
one order call
successful so now when I hit this API
when I invoke this
API order call is successful it reach
till here and if you see the logs
response from product API called from
order service. It print the response
actual it printed this. So now here if
you see all the boilerplate code which
we have written HTTP URL connection URL
like uh stream you have to take care of
response parsing all gone with a single
line. See how easy it become with the
rest template. So what exactly happen
inside rest template we'll see that but
here I will show you this another which
we have left. So sometime which we want
is that I also want I don't want to use
the default connection timeout or ret
time out I want to set it. So we can set
it like this while the same thing during
configuration while I'm creating a so
here we have to set the factory
object. This is the factory object. So
here while creating a new rest template
object we have to set a factory object
simple client HTTP request factory
object right. So this factory
ultimately help us
to simple client
HTTP request factory. So as from the
name clear client HTTP request factory.
So this factory ultimately help us to
return the object
of client
HTTP
request right which ultimately kind of
where we can set all our URL your
timeouts your post method right
ultimately all this so generally HTTP
URL connection internally also has this
request Okay. So the same thing. So I am
creating I'm using this simple client
HTTP request directory which is a
default you can say that here I haven't
used new rest
template.
Okay. So but how I will get the request
object client HTTP request object. So
internally by default it uses this
factory only. I will show you the flow.
By default it uses this factory only and
set the default values.
Okay. So now if I want to take some
control, so this is how it does like I
created a factory object and I set the
what is the connection timeout, what is
the read time out and put this
factory.
Okay. So these timeouts are in
milliseconds. So this is just I want to
show you here. Otherwise if you don't
want to set the connection timeout, read
timeout, you can directly use just new
rest template. That's all.
But how this exactly happened? How it
worked internally? I just wrote one
line object rest template object get for
object and pass the
URI and uh this response type and it
worked. The connection is
made. So what happened internally? So
understand this flow very properly. If
you understand the plain Java flow, this
would be like exactly the same thing
which it does behind the
framework. So first thing when we call
rest template dot get for object, what
it does it it first invokes create
request. Okay, I told you the default
is simple HTTP client request factory.
So it will call a create request method
on top of it. Okay. So the request goes
to
here. Now what it does is it will create
us an HTTP URL connection object. Okay.
Earlier in the plain Java we were
creating the object HTTP URL connection
object. Now it's got hidden inside this.
So this factory is creating an object
for us. HTTP URL connection object. Now
it said request method connect time out
read timeout whatever here we have like
get connect time out ret time out
whatever then what it will return is it
will return us a simple HTTP
request object set the connection HTTP
URL connection object inside it and
return this
object. it send me the simple client
HTTP request in return. So this object
internally has this HTTP URL connection.
HTTP URL connection object this has it.
Okay. And then HTTP URL connection we
already know that it is a kind of an
envelope where we have
URI method read timeout connect time out
everything.
Okay. So now rest template again got
this request object. What it will call
is second it call execute
on this request object. This request
object it calls execute. So this is the
class you can go to this class and check
this. It is exactly the same thing you
will find. So it will help you more
clear. You can put some debugger point.
So now if you go to a simple client HTTP
request object and go to its execute
method what it will do it will take out
the HTTP URL connection object which we
have created and calls
connection.connect. I told you what
connection.connect does is it actually
creates the TCP connection. So it but
one thing I told you if you got the flow
of plain Java connection right properly
it do not blindly create an
HTTP client which is a wrapper around
TCP is do not blindly create an object
of
it there is some cache involved in it
keep alive cache I told you in protocol
1.1 HTTP protocol 1.1 keep alive cache
is true set so it first internally
invokes this keep live cache class. So
this has two methods get and put. So
first it goes to the get and check if
this URL and port number exist whatever
we are trying to hit. Okay. If yes then
means there is already a HTTP client
object or you can say the TCP connection
object is present. So reuse it because
if it is there in the cache means it is
still alive means its timeout is not yet
happen or maximum limit is not yet
crossed. Okay but if it is not there
right so we have to create a new HTTP
client object or you can say that new
TCP connection object we have to create
and we have to also put into the
cache. Okay. So first what it will do is
it will take out the HTTP URL connection
object and then invoke the connect which
actually creates the TCP connection but
it do not create blindly it first check
the cache. Now once you have get the
HTTP client object which is present
inside a connection it will call get
response code. I told you that there are
three methods like get input stream, get
response code or dot connect. So dot
connect is used to do a TCP connection
and get input stream and get response
code is like where client send the
request get the
response. Okay, response stream it
got now it has to do a
parsing. So after that it invoke get
response code means it now send the
request to the server
also and wait for the
response. Okay. So now all the response
stream whatever the response it has got
from the client or server it's there all
in the connection that stream would be
there. Okay. So it's there and it return
it's set inside simple client HTTP
response object and set this URL
connection this connection which has all
this response info right it's set inside
this response object and returns. So now
I am got simple client HTTP response
object. This has internally HTTP URL
connection
object. Now I am doing is handling the
response and extract data.
So here whatever you have defined like
what type you wanted response I want to
parse the response as a string or let's
say some class product class.
Now it does parsing for us. Automatic
parsing. So it still got a stream. It
read the stream and it will do a
parsing. So it will use some JSON
converters
possibly. And once that done it
ultimately close the reading stream.
Okay. But here if you notice do not
close the TCP connection. It is not
doing u HTTP
client that close or something. It's
not. So this is our HTTP client. It's
not closing it. It just closed the
stream. As soon as the stream is closed,
what happen is the HTTP client object
which is our TCP
connection, right? Which is there in the
cache. Let's say currently it's marked
as in use equals to true. Now that would
be like false. Now it is not in use. It
is marked as free. Now it can be reused
again till
its configurations are met properly.
So here if you see
that rest template does all the things
which we were doing it manually in the
plain
java opening a connection setting all
this timeouts
uh calling connect internally does it.
So calling internally the request
sending the request getting the response
parsing it closing the request stream
response
stream but it's all replaced with just
one line in spring
boot get for
object this one line this whole
frameworks now handling
it okay so what are some of the other
method which are available in rest
template I told you this get for object
Similarly there is something called get
for entity. So in get for object
whatever the response type you are
sending it return the response body as
an object. So here if you see I see
product.class the return would be
product body only. It will give me the
response body only not the complete
response. Complete response as status
headers everything. But this returns me
get for object return me only the body
the
response actual data response. There is
something called get for
entity URL and the response type. So it
will give me the full response entity
the same rest template dot get for
entity just
the your
URI okay the complete URI and the type
which you wanted in the response
product.class class but the response
type is the complete entity. Okay. So
now in the response you can get the
status code also you can get the headers
and you can get the body. Your body
would be of type this
this. Okay. The only difference is that
in the first one you get only this body
not status not headers anything like
that.
For the post you have to use this method
post for object. Okay. So it has your
URI the request because in the post you
have to pass the request body and the
response type. Very very simple. Again
if you see rest templated post for
object your URI. This is my URI which I
want to hit. This is
the request body which I want to send
because I want to create a new product.
Right? So I create a new product. I
create one object which has this values.
I send this to the server and my
response body would be like this
product.class. Okay. Again post for
object means it only the response body
would be available to you. In the
response it would be direct
body. But post for entity means full.
The response type would be response
entity. From there you can get a body.
You can get a status code. can read
headers. So sim similarly for put we
have a URL and the request. So here if
you see send put and no response body is
expected in the put you won't get any
response right because it's only an
update. So this is let's say
URL
right rest template.put output URL and
the updated product whatever you want to
update it like here generally it would
have ID also this ID this ID let's say
this is the product which you want to
update but there is no return
type similarly for delete you have to
just give the URI the URL so here if you
see that you provided the URL and just
say that delete and there is no return
type okay so So there are two more
methods general method which give you
more flexibility one is exchange and
another is
execute. So
exchange if you want to customize the
HTTP method according to yourself. If
you want to take control of the header
and the body
yourself but want to rely on a spring
there automatic conversion response
conversion serialization right then you
can go for exchange. Just see an example
here I have defined a
URL. Now I want to take a control of the
header. So now I am creating a one
header object.
Okay, in the header I set the content
type. If any other header I want to set,
let's say authorization header and my
token I have to set here. All the header
you can set
here. Then body. So I have created one.
Let's say this is the body. Some product
and name and the price I have
set. Now in the HTTP entity I have set
both the body and the header.
So now I have full control over my
header and my body how I want it
right and here I am just calling the
exchange. So here pass the URL which you
want to hit. Okay second is HTTP entity
object. HTTP entity object has two
things your body and your header right.
So HTTP entity has two things body and
header. So second is my after HTTP
method it's my HTTP
entity. Okay. And after that response
type in the response which you will get
from the server its body should be
automatically converted to this
product.class. So we're doing automatic
conversion.
Okay. Okay. So the exchange returns you
the response entity which means you have
the complete header access body access
everything. Okay. So this is clearly
understood right when to use exchange
exchange in simple term only use when
you want control over HTTP method header
body but don't want to do conversion
response conversion serialization and
all you want to rely on spring boot then
you can use
this there is one more call execute
which says that hey even the
serialization conversion also you take
care of it it's like a plain
Java how we used to connect right
generally it's like the same thing we
only have to manually do all the things
we have to take care of
the object like header body request
response serialization all need to be
handled manually right so it provide us
complete uh few of the interface request
call back interface and response
extractor interface
The request call back interface if you
see it has functional interface. So we
will use lambda expression but we have
access to client http request object. So
we can modify the request as we want.
Similarly the request response extractor
again it's a function interface which
provide us the access to response object
means we can pass the response as we
want.
So this is an example like I have
already covered in Java the functional
interface and the lambda expression how
to use it. So you can check in depth
there. So here I am creating a new rest
template object first my
URL. Now here if you see what is the I
need an object of this request call back
and the response extractor. So these are
functional interface. So I'm using
lambda expression.
So means here at this point of time I
have access to request. So what I'm
doing is request using lambda expression
I'm writing my functionality here now.
So in the request I am changing the
header I am adding my body which I
wanted right and here if you see that I
am taking care of serialization now it's
not automatically done. So whatever the
object I have created product I have to
convert it into a bytes and I have to
put this uh whatever the body which I
have written right bytes input stream
and I have to write it to this body
request
body. Okay so I am doing taking care of
all the serialization and
conversion. Okay. So this is the request
call back nothing but a functional
interface which provide access to client
HTTP request object which where we can
add header add our body but also we need
to take care of serialization
also. Similarly the response which comes
means response extractor. So we have
access to the response client HTTP
response. So here I'm using again lambda
expression. So whatever the response I
will get. So this is my input
stream. Whatever the response dot get
body stream util do.copy to string I am
just copying to string that's all. So my
body would be like become a string
response extractor this one. Okay. And
this is ultimately where I am invoking
execute. So internally it will do
connect first. It will create a TCP
connection and then it will send get
response code right and uh
then have this request and header
properly set into the uh HTTP
client connection object. Okay. And then
it get a response and then it will do
this. It will run this
logic. Whatever the response it will
get, it will run then this logic. Okay.
And if you see print it, it will print
properly. Okay. So in short use exchange
again very very
important when you only have to worry
about headers and body. But internal one
level more depth like
serialization right and uh conversion
you don't have to worry about it. You
just send like what you wanted. It it
automatically does all the parsing.
That's all. But when you want full
control like actually execute right
everybody call internally execute only
even if you say
exchange put post get all internally
call execute only
internally right. So if you want full
control then you can use execute and you
can use this is one simple example.
Okay. So when execute got invoked it do
connect and then it will try to create a
HTTP connection object which will give
you an HTTP client
request has this object HTTP client
request. So then it this is get invoke.
Now you have the
request you update headers and
body. Okay. After that it makes get
response
code. Now once it made response code it
got a response. So after response what
it has to do it run
this parts like this and ultimately you
get a
response. Okay if you practice this you
will get to know like u very very easy
to
understand but what are the limitation
of rest template why we call it as
legacy or traditional way of
communication in spring
application. So the one of the biggest
problem which I feel is in the rest
template there are so many overloaded
method. So this method which I have
covered right execute, exchange, delete,
put, post, post for object, get for
entity, get for object. These are you
can say that very very few methods I
have covered. Even for get for object
you will see three overloaded method.
For get for entity you will find three
overloaded methods. Similarly for this,
similarly for this, similarly for this
there are so many overloaded method. You
get confused man. which one to use when
and also it's very difficult to remember
and maintain also. So this is one of the
biggest
challenge. Second is rest template was
built before the concept like retry,
circuit breaker etc. So yes there is a
support present into the rest template
but
it's more you can know that more
overloaded methods are there. That's why
I tell you that if you want to use a
circuit breaker functionality you will
find one overloaded method for this for
this because you have to support for all
any new feature you have to add just see
that any new feature you have to add you
have to add for all the flavors get post
put delete exchange so means like you
have to keep on adding the overloaded
methods for each of the new
functionality you
introduce so it's not user friendly to
use and it is not easy to remember, not
easy to maintain. So that's why rest
template is in maintenance mode. No new
feature only bug fixes because nowadays
in the HTTP request itself there are so
many new new features coming like this
functionality this functionality like
filtering interceptor functionality. So
means they are not keep on appending new
functionalities here. Now that's where
the rest client comes into the picture.
Okay, so we will cover rest line into
the next
video. But in short it's follow a
builder style API or we can always say
that fluent API like there is no
overloaded you can say that methods we
don't have to remember it just like get
put post that's all if you have to do a
get method no matter get for entity get
for object doesn't it provide us the
complete
functionality so very easy to maintain
userfriendly and more readable code
Right? We will see that how the fluent
and builder style API we have seen.
Okay. and all the latest support it
provide an easy integration like
interceptor filters very easy
integrations are present right those
integration might be also present with
rest template but it's not like that
easy there you there might be like some
overloaded method which you have to know
and see lot of parameter you have to
pass to use that it is possible I'm not
saying it's not possible but it's not
easy with restclient you will see that
those things are very very
easy. So we'll see you in rest client
video in the next part and we will also
come to the
main this
this spring cloud way of communicating
between the microser f
client. Okay so any doubt let me know in
the comment section we'll discuss
further. Thank you. Bye.